Soumya Nair

Mumbai | +91 7738040214 nairsoumya001@gmail.com | www.linkedin.com/in/soumya-n/

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

A highly committed and hard-working professional with over 12 years of R & D experience in the Biopharma industry. Specializes in cloning, mammalian cell culture and protein purification. Good organization and project management skills. Upholds high moral values and passionate about making a positive impact in society.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Manager

Reliance Life Sciences

April 2018 to August 2021

- Stable cell line generation of SARS CoV-2 protein expressing CHO clones; developed more than 9 clones within 4 months
- **In-house ELISA** development for antigen quantification resulting in more than 80% cost reduction
- Purified 4 model viruses for viral clearance studies
- Established a high throughput **single cell cloning** process
- Analyzed images of more than 85000 different clones for evaluating clonality
- Clone productivity analysis by ELISA
- Generated more than **56 stable clones** by transfection via electroporation, nucleofection and chemical agents
- Comparative evaluation of the Lonza versus Horizon CHO expression platforms
- Protein expression & purification of candidates for targeted delivery
- Cell bank characterization by Realtime PCR assays and NGS

Deputy Manager

Reliance Life Sciences

April 2015 to March 2018

 Optimized Single Cell Cloning by microscopy and by the limiting dilution method

EDUCATION

Reliance Institute of Life Sciences

August 2009 to July 2010 80.35 % in Advanced Diploma Program in Biotherapeutics

Rai University (YCMOU)

August 2004 to June 2008
First class in B.Tech Biotechnology

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Cell line development
- Gene Transfections transient & stable
- Single Cell Cloning
- CHOK1SV GS-KO platform Lonza & Horizon
- Bacterial Protein expression
- Protein Chromatography
- Bioassays
- Recombinant DNA Technology
- Sanger DNA Sequencing, Next Generation Sequencing
- Real-Time PCR
- Viral clearance studies
- Electronic Lab notebook

STRENGTHS

- Good team player
- GII
- Report, CTD, SOP, dossier writing
- Ability to meet stringent deadlines
- Excellent presentation skills
- Fast learner, resourceful
- Easy adaptability to change
- Imparting training

Soumya Nair

Mumbai | +91 7738040214 nairsoumya001@gmail.com | www.linkedin.com/in/soumya-n/

WORK EXPERIENCE ... CONTINUED

- Fulfilment of FDA requirements for assurance of monoclonality of clones
- Generated 23 different single cell clones within 1 year
- Developed and optimized cell based assays
- Implemented **electronic lab notebook (ELN)** in R & D with IT support, within 1 year

Executive

Reliance Life Sciences

August 2010 to March 2015 (on contract from 2010-2011)

- Viral assays like plaque assay, TCID50
- · siRNA transfections and knockdown studies
- Development of novel candidates for siRNA delivery
- Cloning and expression of genes in bacteria under the T7 promoter and subsequent downstream processing
- DNA and RNA based techniques like extraction, in-vitro transcription, quantitation, PCRs, sequencing
- Protein estimation and purification, SDS PAGE and Western Blotting

PUBLICATIONS

- siRNAs encapsulated in recombinant capsid protein derived from Dengue serotype 2 virus inhibits the four serotypes of the virus and proliferation of cancer cells. J Biotechnol.;193:23-33. 2015 Jan 10
- Infant mouse brain passaged Dengue serotype 2 virus induces non-neurological disease with inflammatory spleen collapse in AG129 mice after splenic adaptation. Virus Res.;173(2):386-97. 2013 May

INSTRUMENT HANDLING

In order of decreasing proficiency

- Clone Select Imager
- AKTA (Prime, Explorer and Go)
- Thermal cycler
- Sorvall centrifuge
- TFF system
- FACSCalibur
- qPCR system

CO-CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

- SAP material management
- In-charge of the Document Management System
- Active member of several committees like the Retreat Team, Environment Management System Committee, Electronic Lab Notebook Team
- Sports co-ordinatorship
- Event hosting
- Interfacing between the research and IT Teams

CERTIFICATIONS

- Labware ELN Instrument data mapping
- IBM Data Science Orientation
- IBM Data Science Methodologies
- Best Oral Presentation
- Prizes in sports and cultural events